Finding Aid for the Eiko Ishioka papers LSC.2288
UCLA Library Special Collections
Eiko Ishioka papers
1955-2012
UCLA Library Special Collections
Ishioka, Eiko
LSC.2288
859.75 linear feet (275 document boxes, 63 record cartons, 116 flat boxes, 66 oversize flat boxes, 11 shoe boxes, 37 telescope boxes, 129 oversized folders, 39 film and video canisters)
173 Gigabytes (digital files from 289 discs)
3 born-digital carriers (1 unprocessed DVD, 2 unprocessed 5.25 inch floppy disks)
Material in this collection relates to the career of the multi-faceted designer Eiko Ishioka, encompassing her work in the performing arts, especially on various stage productions; for exhibitions, fashion shows, and athletic teams; in advertising; and in book, periodical, record cover, and product and packaging design. Items include costume drawings and sketches, set design drawings, performance production records and photographs, and fabric samples. The collection also contains numerous posters, photographs, slides, transparencies, negatives, and production material pertaining to design projects and advertising campaigns, as well as audiovisual and born-digital material. Additionally some items relate to Ishioka's student work in Tokyo, including artwork, design projects and photographs.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS DIGITAL, AUDIO, AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed digital and audiovisual materials. Digital, audio, and audiovisual materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed digital, audio, and audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nico Soultanakis, 2014-2015.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9977558583606533
Biography/History
Eiko Ishioka was born on July 12, 1938 in Tokyo, Japan and attended the Tokyo National University of Fine Arts and Music, studying in the Design Department of the Faculty of Fine Arts. She graduated in 1961, and started her career designing advertising campaigns for the Japanese cosmetics giant Shiseido. In 1970, Ishioka founded her own design firm and soon diversified her work by adding books and journals (including those published by Kadokawa Books), magazine articles, record album covers, and product packaging to her repertoire, as well as serving as stage director of several Issey Miyake fashion shows. Her firm also created numerous advertising campaigns for major clients such as the department store chain Parco throughout the 1970s.
Ishioka soon branched out into the performing arts, and she spent the last several decades of her career mainly designing costumes and/or sets for theater, film, opera, and individual performers. Some of her major stage credits include the Broadway productions M. Butterfly (1988) and David Copperfield's Dreams & Nightmares (1996); the Nederlander Opera's The Ring of Nibelung (1997-1998); Cirque du Soleil's Varekai (2002); and singer Grace Jones' Hurricane tour (2009). Film credits include production work for Paul Schrader's Mishima: A Life in Four Chapters (1985) and costumes designed for a number of Tarsem (Tarsem Singh) films, as well as for Francis Ford Coppola's Bram Stoker's Dracula (1992), which garnered her an Oscar. In addition, Ishioka curated exhibitions, including the photography exhibitions Nuba (1980) and Life (1992) regarding the work of German filmmaker and photographer Leni Riefenstahl, and she contributed to the multi-media art installation Tokyo: Form & Spirit (1986). She also designed sports uniforms for the NBA and Olympic athletes. Along with these various endeavors, Ishioka continued with advertising work, and with book and record cover design, including the Grammy-winning cover of Miles Davis' Tutu (1986). She compiled and designed two books that focused on her career: Eiko by Eiko (1983) and Eiko on Stage (2000).
Eiko Ishioka was married to Nico Soultanakis. She died on January 21, 2012, in Tokyo, Japan.
Scope and Content
Material in the Eiko Ishioka papers relates to nearly every aspect of the designer's multi-faceted career. Her work in the performing arts is documented through costume drawings and sketches, set design drawings, research material, production records and photographs, fabric samples, and audiovisual material for numerous stage projects, including the Broadway productions M. Butterfly (1988) and David Copperfield: Dreams & Nightmares (1996), the operas Chushingura (1997) and The Ring of the Nibelung (1997-1998), and Cirque du Soleil's Varekai (2002). Although this collection holds little material relating to her work in film, it does contain original costume design drawings and sketches for Bram Stoker's Dracula (1992), as well as several posters designed by Ishioka for the Japanese releases of that film, Apocalypse Now, and others. In addition, the collection documents other varied projects including the curation of exhibitions dedicated to the life and work of Leni Riefenstahl, Nuba (1980) and Life (1992); posters designed for inclusion in or as advertising for numerous exhibitions; and several collaborations with fashion designer Issey Miyake in the 1970s.
This collection also documents Ishioka's design of books, particularly Eiko by Eiko (1983); journals, including Wild Times, and magazine articles; record album covers, especially Miles Davis' Tutu; and products and packaging, through production material such as photographs, drawings, layouts, and proofs, as well as final products. A small amount of material pertains to her work designing athletic uniforms, including for the Houston Rockets NBA team, the 2002 Winter Olympics in Salt Lake City, and costumes for the opening ceremony of the 2008 Summer Olympics in Beijing.
Ishioka's decades-long career in advertising is well-represented in this collection through numerous posters, photographs, slides, transparencies, digital, and audiovisual items, primarily for campaigns designed for the Japanese companies Shiseido, Parco, Kadokawa Books, Diana shoes, Kissa, Tokyu, Sanyo Fashion House, and others from the 1960s-1980s.
The collection contains numerous items created while Ishioka was a student at the Tokyo National University of Fine Arts and Music, including artwork (drawings, sketches, paintings) and production material pertaining to design projects, as well as snapshots of various excursions and activities during this time period. In addition, material documenting her overall career through photographs, portfolios, awards, publicity, and art supplies, is also present. Finally, the collection contains Ishioka's voluminous library of art, design, and other books.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Early work Series 2: Stage projects Series 3: Moving image projects Series 4: Exhibitions and events Series 5: Fashion and uniforms Series 6: Book Design Series 7: Periodical design Series 8: Record cover design Series 9: Advertising Series 10: Products and packaging Series 11: Audiovisual and born-digital material Series 12: Career Series 13: Personal Series 14: Works by others Series 15: Books from the library of Eiko Ishioka Series 16: Preservation posters
Separated Material
The David Copperfield: Dreams & Nightmares set model was separated and transferred to The Magic of David Copperfield in Las Vegas, 2023. The Varekai costumes were separated and transferred to UCLA School of Theater, Film and Television, 2023.
Related Material
Eiko Ishioka papers, Margaret Herrick Library, Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, Beverly Hills.
Other Finding Aids
Item-level inventories for posters and audiovisual material are available.
Costume design; Theaters -- Stage setting and scenery; Advertising -- Japan.; Set designers. -- Archives.; Costume designers. -- Archives.; Art direction.
- Series 1: Early work, circa 1955-1966
  Scope and Content
  This series consists primarily of early art and design work, much of it created while a student at Tokyo National University of Fine Arts and Music, and related material. Artwork includes sketches, works on paper (especially watercolor and crayon), and paintings. Also present is various material relating to several design projects. In addition, the series contains numerous photographs, the handmade book "Eco's Life Story," several scrapbooks and notebooks, and a small amount of school and early career documents.
  - Subseries 1.1: Artwork, circa 1958-1961
    Sketches and works on paper are in ink, pencil, charcoal, oil crayon, watercolor, and paint. Paintings are primarily still lifes, street scenes, and landscapes. Boxes 118-123 are oversized folders, most with a single item.
    - Sketchbook, circa 1958 (Box 127)
    - Sketches, circa 1958-1961 (Box 129, Folder 2)
    - Works on paper, 1958, circa 1958-1961 (Box 118, Box 119, Box 120, Box 121, Box 122, Box 123, Box 129, Folder 3-5, Box 174, Folder 2-4, Box 182, Folder 1-2)
    - Paintings, circa 1958-1961 (Box 739, Box 740)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Held onsite at YRL.
    - Sketchbook (empty), circa 1958 (Box 174, Folder 10)
      Used as storage for loose items in box 174 folders 3-4.
  - Subseries 1.2: Design, circa 1958-1961
    Subseries consists of drawings and other material for design projects for various objects; also abstract graphic design material. Photographs and contact sheets are primarily images of graphic design.
    - Projects, 1958-1961, undated (Box 124, Folder 1-4, Box 129, Folder 7-11, Box 174, Folder 1, Box 182, Folder 3)
      Material includes technical drawings for a teapot, cookware and mobile toy, artwork for lamp and flashlight designs (all in box 129), as well as artwork of repetitive design variations.
    - Calendar (woodcuts), undated (Box 129, Folder 6)
    - Mounted toy designs, undated (Box 741, Box 742, Box 743)
    - Book jacket, 1959 (Box 127)
    - Posters (hand-painted advertising), undated (Box 719)
      Held onsite at YRL (map folder, top drawer of map file drawers in Coleman Room).
    - Yes No No Yes poster, undated (Box 37)
    - Poster proofs and drawings, undated (Box 129, Folder 15)
    - Photographs and contact sheets, circa 1958-1961 (Box 124, Folder 5, Box 126, Folder 1, Box 129, Folder 12-14)
      Includes some drawings.
    - Negatives, circa 1958-1961 (Box 124, Folder 6)
    - Mounted Isetan design, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 182, Folder 11)
  - Subseries 1.3: Photographs, circa 1955-1971
    Primarily black-and-white snapshots of Ishioka and friends/schoolmates, including various beach, skiing, and other excursions in Japan. Binder contains selected early photos, some annotated. Negatives are primarily of personal snapshots; some are of early posters, projects, or ads, and publicity shots of Ishioka.
    Arrangement
    Where possible, photographs that appeared to be of the same event or excursion, or from the same film roll, were grouped together. There are also a few topical groupings, as well as a small number of photos of Ishioka with student work.
    - Artwork and design, circa 1958-1961 (Box 124, Folder 10)
    - Notebook (artwork/design studies), circa 1958-1961 (Box 124, Folder 7)
    - Photobooth pictures, 1960s (Box 124, Box 11)
    - Subject/roll groupings, circa 1955-1965 (Box 124, Folder 12-14)
    - Unsorted, circa 1955-1965 (Box 125, Folder 1-6)
    - Binder, circa 1955-1971 (Box 125, Folder 7)
    - Slides, circa 1959-1966, undated (Box 485, Folder 1, Box 499)
    - Negatives, 1960s-1970s (Box 709, Box 712, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 1.4: "Eco's Life Story", undated (Box 128, Box 129, Folder 1)
    Unpublished book created by Ishioka of stories from her childhood in collage form, primarily in English.
  - Subseries 1.5: Notebooks and scrapbooks, circa 1955 (Box 124, Folder 8-9, Box 126, Folder 2-6, Box 127)
    Scrapbooks pertain to design, volleyball and sumo wrestling (box 126), and Hollywood stars (box 127).
  - Subseries 1.6: School and early career documents, 1957-circa 1961 (Box 128, Folder 1)
    Includes early résumé with photograph.
  - Subseries 1.7: Ephemera, 1961-1966 (Box 169, Folder 9)
    Programs for jazz and other concerts, film and stage events.
- Series 2: Stage projects, 1974-2009
  This series contains material documenting Ishioka's costume and set design work on various stage projects including plays, operas, musicals, and other performances. Material typically includes research clippings and images, costume sketches and drawings, set design drawings, production images, and performance clippings and ephemera. Some subseries also contain scripts and other project development material. Ishioka's work on M. Butterfly (1988), David Copperfield: Dreams & Nightmares (1996), and The Ring of Nibelung (1998-1999), is especially well-documented. Also present is a small amount of material for unrealized or unidentified stage projects. For items relating to Issey Miyake fashion shows, see Series 5.
  See also Series 11 for related audiovisual material.
  Series is arranged chronologically by project.
  - Subseries 2.1: Histoire du Soldat, 1974
    Contains material related to Ishioka's art direction, and set and costume design for production at Seibu Theater, Tokyo.
    - Slides and transparencies, circa 1974 (Box 450, Folder 1, Box 451, Box 466)
    - Negatives, circa 1974 (Box 712, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 2.2: Hamlet, 1976
    - Photographs and negatives, circa 1976 (Box 130, Folder 1-2)
    - Slides and transparencies, circa 1976 (Box 450, Folder 2-3, Box 451, Box 466, Folder 1)
    - Poster, 1976 (Box 27)
  - Subseries 2.3: Salomé, 1978
    - Photographs and negatives, circa 1978 (Box 130, Folder 1-2, Box 712, Folder 3)
    - Slides and transparencies, circa 1978 (Box 450, Folder 4, Box 451, Box 452, Box 453, Box 466, Folder 1)
    - Poster, 1978 (Box 19)
  - Subseries 2.4: M. Butterfly, 1986-1990
    This subseries contains material for both costume and set design for the original Broadway production (Eugene O'Neill Theater), as well as some material for subsequent proudctions in London and Tokyo. Costume items include research clippings, sketches, color drawings (that do not appear to be done by Ishioka), a kimono mock-up, fabric samples, a hair piece, and a peacock feather. Set designs are documented by numerous technical drawings as well as various material relating to show curtains. Also present are scripts, production images, and some publicity material. See Series 11 for related audiovisual material.
    - Scripts, 1986, circa 1988 (Box 130, Folder 3-5)
    - Documents and notes, 1987-1989 (Box 130, Folder 6)
    - Research clippings, undated (Box 130, Folder 7, Box 164, Folder 1)
    - Research and set photographs, undated (Box 130, Folder 8)
    - Costume design: research clippings and sketches (peacock), circa 1988 (Box 170, Folder 3)
      Includes a peacock feather.
    - Costume design: sketches and patterns, circa 1988 (Box 170, Folder 1-2)
    - Costume design: drawings, circa 1988 (Box 164, Folder 2-7)
    - Costume design: annotated drawings (copies), undated (Box 164, Folder 8-9)
    - Costume design: drawings and transparencies (butterfly kimono), 1988 (Box 182, Folder 4-5)
    - Costume design: photographs, circa 1988, 1989 (Box 130, Folder 9)
      Annotated with color samples. Also includes some correspondence.
    - Costume design: kimono mock-up and fabric samples, circa 1988 (Box 710)
    - Costume design: hair piece, circa 1988 (Box 710)
    - Fabric samples, undated (Box 130, Folder 10)
    - Set design: sketches and drawings, circa 1988 (Box 173, Folder 1)
    - Set design (Broadway): technical drawings (preliminary plans/bid), 1987 (Box 182, Folder 6)
    - Set design (Broadway): technical drawings, circa 1987 (Box 111)
    - Set design (UK): technical drawings, 1988-1989 (Box 182, Folder 7)
    - Set design (Japan): technical drawings, circa 1989 (Box 164, Folder 10-11, Box 182, Folder 8)
    - Set design: show curtains, circa 1987-1988, 1988 (Box 110, Box 164, Folder 12, Box 170, Folder 4, Box 182, Folder 9-10)
      Items are for butterfly and Chinese Cultural Revolution curtains.
    - Set design: show curtains (original Chinese posters), undated (Box 112)
    - Set design: furniture, 1987 (Box 164, Folder 13)
    - Production photographs (copies), undated (Box 130, Folder 11)
    - Production photographs (binder), circa 1988 (Box 466, Folder 2)
      Also includes some contact sheets, negatives, and drawings.
    - Production slides and transparencies (binders), undated (Box 130, Folder 12, Box 131, Folder 1, Box 466, Folder 2)
    - Production slides, circa 1988 (Box 453)
    - Programs and flyers, 1988-1989 (Box 131, Folder 2-3)
      For productions in New York, London, Washington DC, and Japan.
    - Publicity and clippings, 1988-1989 (Box 156, Folder 1, Box 517, Folder 4, Box 704)
    - Lobby cards, 1988 (Box 173, Folder 2)
    - Ephemera, 1988-1990 (Box 131, Folder 4)
    - Notes (empty slide binders), circa 1988 (Box 466, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2.5: The Making of the Representative for Planet 8, 1988
    Contains material related to set and costume design for production at the Houston Grand Opera. Production photograph binders also include slides, transparencies, and negatives. Some photographs are copies.
    - Production memos and publicity, 1988 (Box 131, Folder 5)
    - Music and libretto, 1988, undated (Box 131, Box 6)
    - Sketches and notes, circa 1988 (Box 165, Folder 1-5)
    - Production photographs (binders), 1988 (Box 131, Folder 7, Box 466, Folder 4)
    - Publicity and clippings, 1988 (Box 516, Folder 3, Box 704)
  - Subseries 2.6: The Screens, 1988-1990
    Contains material related to costume design for production at the Guthrie Theater, Minneapolis (JoAnne Akalaitis, director). See Series 11 Subseries 11.3 for related audio material.
    - Script, 1988 (Box 131, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box 131, Folder 9)
    - Character and scene notes, 1988 (Box 156, Folder 2)
    - Costume design (binder), circa 1989 (Box 132, Folder 1-3)
      Includes sketches, notes, and some fabric swatches.
    - Costume design: drawings and fabric swatches, circa 1989 (Box 173, Folder 3-8)
    - Costume design: photographs, circa 1989 (Box 132, Folder 4)
    - Costume design: slides (binder), 1989 (Box 467, Folder 1-2)
    - Production photographs and slides (binder), 1989 (Box 132, Folder 5-6)
    - Production photographs (binder), 1989 (Box 467, Folder 3)
    - Programs, 1989 (Box 132, Folder 7)
    - Other Akalaitis production photographs, circa 1987 (Box 132, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 2.7: L'Inhumaine, 1990
    Contains material relating to Ishioka's stage direction of production at Orchard Hall, Tokyo. See Series 11 for audiovisual material.
    - Production photographs, circa 1990 (Box 132, Folder 9, Box 133, Folder 1)
    - Production photographs (binders), circa 1990 (Box 133, Folder 2-3, Box 467, Folder 4-5)
      Binders also contain slides and transparencies.
    - Poster, 1990 (Box 15)
  - Subseries 2.8: Sansho the Bailiff, 1993
    Contains material relating to Brooklyn Academy of Music Fall Workshop.
    - Outline and set notes, 1993 (Box 174, Folder 8)
    - Production photographs, circa 1993 (Box 133, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 2.9: David Copperfield: Dreams & Nightmares, 1991-2004
    This subseries contains material for both costume and set designs for production at the Martin Beck Theatre (New York), including research clippings and images, sketches and drawings, a costume design binder, and a 3-D set model. Also present are production photographs and other performance-related material.
    - Script, 1996 (Box 133, Folder 5)
    - Research clippings and images, 1994-2004 (Box 133, Folder 6)
    - Research clippings and images (bat), 1991, undated (Box 133, Folder 7)
    - Performance modules, circa 1996, 2004 (Box 133, Folder 8)
    - Costume design (binder), circa 1996 (Box 133, Folder 9-10, Box 134, Folder 1)
      Binder includes sketches, notes, photographs, measurements, and fabric swatches.
    - Costume and set design: sketches and drawings, circa 1996 (Box 170, Folder 5-8)
      Includes some clippings, scene panels.
    - Set design: preliminary, 1996 (Box 134, Folder 2)
    - Set design: preliminary (with added notes and sketches), 1996 (Box 134, Folder 3)
    - Set design: technical drawings, bid documents, 1996 (Box 599)
    - Set design: drawings, circa 1996 (Box 183, Folder 1)
    - Set design: drawings (copies), undated (Box 134, Folder 4)
    - Set design: drawings (mounted copies), undated (Box 186)
    - Set design: fabric swatch, 1996 (Box 134, Folder 5)
    - Set construction: photographs, circa 1996 (Box 134, Folder 6-11)
    - Production photographs, 1997 (Box 161, Folder 5)
    - Production photographs (binder), 1996 (Box 134, Folder 12)
      Includes negatives and slides.
    - Production photographs and drawings (copies), undated (Box 135, Folder 1)
    - Production photographs (negatives), undated (Box 161, Folder 6)
    - Opening events photographs, 1996 (Box 135, Folder 2)
    - Novelty photograph (Ishioka levitating), undated (Box 135, Folder 3)
    - Programs, 1996 (Box 135, Folder 5)
    - Clippings, 1994-1996 (Box 135, Folder 4)
    - Ephemera, 1996, undated (Box 135, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2.10: Chushingura, 1996-2001
    Contains material related to set and costume design for the opera production at the Tokyo Bunk Kaikan, directed by Werner Herzog. See also Series 11 for audiovisual material, including recorded conversations with director Herzog.
    - Scripts, 1997 (Box 135, Folder 7-8)
    - Notes and sketches, undated (Box 135, Folder 9)
    - Costume and set design: research clippings and sketches, undated (Box 156, Folder 3)
      Includes notes and some color and fabric samples.
    - Set design: bid drawings, 1996 (Box 156, Folder 4)
    - Production photographs (binders), circa 1997 (Box 135, Folder 10-11, Box 136, Folder 1-2, Box 468, Folder 1-4)
      Binders also include slides, transparencies, and contact sheets. Some also include images of actors posing in costumes.
    - Production photographs (copies), undated (Box 136, Folder 3-4)
    - Photographs: Ishioka and Werner Herzog, circa 1997 (Box 136, Folder 5)
    - Programs, 1997 (Box 136, Folder 6)
    - Flyers, circa 1997 (Box 136, Folder 7)
    - Poster, 1997 (Box 2)
    - Poster and CD cover design, circa 1997 (Box 136, Folder 8)
    - Poster proofs, circa 1997 (Box 183, Folder 2)
    - Poster production material, undated (Box 39)
    - Publicity and clippings, 1997-2001 (Box 137, Folder 1)
  - Subseries 2.11: The Ring of the Nibelung, 1997-2005
    Contains a variety of material documenting costume design for opera production at De Nederlandse Opera, Amsterdam, including research clippings, numerous sketches and color drawings, fitting photographs, fabric samples, and a pattern. Also present are production photographs and other performance-related material, including posters (not designed by Ishioka). See Series 11 for related audiovisual material.
    - Correspondence, 1997-2005 (Box 137, Folder 2)
    - Costume design: research clippings, circa 1997 (Box 165, Folder 6-7)
    - Costume design: research clippings and sketches (with notes), 1998, undated (Box 153, Folder 1-2, Box 165, Folder 8)
    - Costume design: sketches and notes, 1997 (Box 137, Folder 3)
    - Costume design: sketches and notes (notebook), 1998 (Box 137, Folder 4)
    - Costume design: drawings and sketches, circa 1997-1998 (Box 167, Folder 1-6, Box 183, Folder 3)
      Includes some research clippings.